Okay
so now we come to what I think it is in some
sense these the soul of RL okay temporal difference
methods right I think I think TD is very important
semantic we can argue that RL is all about
learning from samples learning to control
dynamic compute complex system by just sampling
from the system and soon so forth in which
case like the Monte Carlo methods we talked
about are also reinforcement learning methods
right but for me what is really cool about
RL is the whole idea of temporal difference
okay to what do temporal difference methods
are many ways we shake and motivate this did
any of you hear me in cinema securities class
last lecture you did what is event count variance
you are securities less.
Yeah there are you are notice you in the class
you keep too quiet or maybe we did not show
up that day you did okay anyway so there are
only processor but he do not count now you
are not taking the class for cadet are you
know even car maybe so I motivated in a very
different way temporal difference is I motivated
in a very different way from a completely
neuroscience or not even Euro sign is more
like a behavioral psychology point of view
okay so now I will do it purely from a computational
point of view right.
So let us start up so what did we do when
we did the dynamic programming right so when
we are thinking about what we did with dynamic
programming you start with some state s right
then you look at all possible outcomes if
you look at all possible outcomes from that
state right so what is so this is all possible
let us say these are actions right so all
possible actions I can take
and all possible outcomes from those actions
right so what does this correspond to make
my p SA right.
So sum over A p SA so that is what this corresponds
to and what does what does this thing's correspond
to this month sum over S’ PS’ is given
s, right so this is essentially what I did
when a dynamic programming right so every
time I did a backup I took the entire possible
outcome right and it took looked at each one
of the state's here I use the values of the
phase and did that back up right I did a backup
so this kind of backups are called
full backups right and it is also distinguished
by the fact that I am using the values here
right this is called
boot strapping I did a full backup and it
did that using bootstrapping.
Okay so next we looked at Monte Carlo method
so what we do in 10 Carlo methods I started
in the state took some action went to another
state took some other action went to another
state I did this till I reach the terminal
state then I use the rewards along the entire
trajectory and updated the value of that state
right so what did I do here these are called
sample backups because I did not take the
full possible set of outcomes I just sampled
an outcome okay it is sampled an outcome and
I do not use any bootstrapping so I do not
use the value of this state update the value
of this state right of course.
In the three such thing we are talking about
we did use bootstrapping but now we are not
using any bootstrapping the plain vanilla
things you do not use any no bootstrapping
correct so what do you think I can do next
bootstrap and sample yeah so I can do sample
backups with bootstrap now will be extreme
that is what is one sample and I will bootstrap
just like we did here one sample but you find
all the way to the end we did no bootstrap
so here what I will do I will start from some
state I will take an action I look at the
next outcome and use the value of the state
to update the value of this state it in the
full backup I do all of this and update there
is no simulation also involved right I am
just using all possible outcomes well here
there is a simulation involved here there
is a simulation involved but here is only
a one-step simulation I just used the value
of this state to back up.
So such methods are called temporal difference
methods why are they called temporal difference
yes the value at T + 1 to get a estimate of
the value at T right so essentially you look
at the prediction you make at time T + 1you
said for changing the prediction you made
at time T right so look at the difference
over time so it is called temporal difference
you look at the difference in predictions
over time we call this call this a temporal
difference production okay hey that is a very
pictorial motivation for why you want to do
something like that okay let us do a little
bit more formal thing right.
.
So if you think about what we did with Monte
Carlo methods is that I was interested in
looking at that right but at every point of
time I had some sample GT okay I did not have
the expected value I just had some value that
they had sample as GT right so if I want to
write this as a stochastic averaging method
right so what will I do I have
so v hat is okay let me not put that little
confuse people a little bit so v hat let me
not put little bit new so I want to form a
new estimate of v hat what will I do I will
take v hat old + some a times right this will
give me we had ? so this is the classical
stochastic averaging rule let me look at from
very beginning you have been see stochastic
averaging rule I told you that almost everything
that we will see later will get converted
to a stochastic averaging rule right.
So this is stochastic averaging version of
what Monte Carlo evaluation right this is
Monte Carlo policy evaluation this is stochastic
averaging version of it right so you can think
of this as old value okay that is target-current
okay so the target – the current prediction
that added to your old prediction gives me
the new prediction right and this is some
form of a error term right okay so I can rule
I can make this me at this is this is what
we say sophistic averaging rule right so in
the Bandit case then we showed you this a
should be 1 / N and all can keep a constant
a on all of those things we talked about it
so this all of you are on board with this
expression.
So this is essentially the incremental version
of simple Monte Carlo simply Monte Carlo estimator
right without all the other complications
I spoke about today no importance sampling
the thing have a policy file and evaluating
the police file target is
this the expected value of GT right the target
does not expected value of GT but I do not
know the expectation I do not know the expected
value of GT so all I have is a sample right
one sample of this quantity of whose expectation
I am taking right so I plug in that sample
here instead of the target yeah no I am talking
about Monte Carlo here I am not talking about
this why I say that is why I kept saying this
is the incremental version of simple MC okay
everybody on board so this is an MC not really
everybody onboard with that.
.
Yes no maybe so now let us go look at this
target fellow closely so what is the target
it is GT right so what is GT going to look
like right so we will do the same trick that
we did earlier okay if I know the true value
actually I do not know the true value I am
going to write this as now can you plug this
into this if I want to I mean right so now
I can say that.
.
Let say everybody on board with that yes no
maybe so notice when new is where the old
is and where the T is and where the T + 1
this is important okay so remember it right
so I do not what you would tell me later that
you are using value at time T to form an estimated
time T +1 very careful you are forming an
estimated time T + 1 so that is why this is
the indicated ? initially I wrote VT and I
erased it wrote ? because I wanted to make
the distinction okay so the value function
estimate is ? estimate but I am making it
for the state I encountered at time T okay.
And I am using the old value I had for the
state I encountered at time T+ 1 right so
this derivation clear right so what we did
here very simple lesson see the same trick
that we use for deriving the bellman updates
right so the same trick I used here except
that I plugged it into instead of plugging
it into the original return equation I plugged
it into the Monte Carlo update alright I use
the same trick let me get into the Monte Carlo
update I get this expression okay so if you
think about it this is exactly what I wrote
here in the picture right.
So I am going to update the value of this
state I will use the reward I get plus the
value at the state
okay so a value I mean a policy evaluation
algorithm that uses this kind of an update
for finding the value function okay is called
a TD(0) algorithm right so you should be able
to write a whole algorithm around this and
be able to implement it and all that right
so you start off with some arbitrary guess
for the value function you have a fixed policy
p you start off with some guess for the value
function then you start generating trajectories
right as you go along the trajectory you keep
updating the value function using this update.
So we come to the end of an episode you go
back reset the state but do not do you reset
the value function okay reset the states and
continue okay so that is essentially what
is going to happen you could have been all
kinds of tricks you could use you could have
an optimistic initial value right you could
do all kinds of different kinds of explorations
on top of the basic policy right if you are
going to use exploration on top of the basic
policy what it should be careful about my
god this is a chapter yeah this is chapter
one question should you should you not if
you know I am talking about valuation here
I am not talking about evaluation here so
I am not talking about control right.
In evaluation you should not I am trying to
evaluate a fixed policy if you update over
an expository action you are evaluating a
different policy right lower excavate reactions
you should not make any updates
so that is basically TD(0) right so we have
done one algorithm this is the basic policy
evaluation algorithm right so people understand
the concept of TD what we are doing here and
looking at things that is one step away and
we are trying to update things okay so let
us
see that is what when you are look when you're
doing then the depth limited rollouts right
in some sense you are doing something like
this right.
.
So when we are thinking about death limited
rollouts is that right I doing depth limited
rollers that is what you are doing I am counting
the reward until I reach a certain point in
time after that I am adding the value function
so that is exactly what you are doing there
right so you can think of this as just one
step prologue not even so it is like it is
take one step and immediately use the value
function is one we are thinking about but
I am doing only one sample and all those are
there done that multiple times but here I
am doing just one sample will come back and
explore this question a little bit later right
in the next chapter will explore this question
where we will explain why the 0 is there.
In is a family of algorithms called TD ? algorithms
where we will actually look at this kind of
having multiple step rewards and then having
the value function case we will talk about
that next time yeah well you
did not ask me that question when we are doing
Monte Carlo no do I am asked I am asked you
to think about what we did in the Monte Carlo
case right so we started in some state s right
we generated an entire trajectory and we use
that update this value so I'm instead of generating
meant a trajectory and they substituting this
GT with a biased sample but I am still measuring
the return starting from s st okay.
Because I am not measuring the return from
st + 1 tray tax could update the values st
+1 but not using this expression I will not
use st +2 here no how no why am I getting
a estimate of we had a st +1 from V hat of
st see v had of st +1 if I do not have any
loops in my state space we have a v+1 will
not even have v st in this expression only
way we had a V st will enter into the expression
for V out of st +1 if you come back to st
right but I see the you know it is a time
index random variable so we will never come
back to st Kalman filter you're trying to
predict what the next state is going to be
right.
So here I am not doing that prediction right
so if you want you can write a kalman filter
like equation here to predict what the next
state would be what I am trying to predict
here what I am trying to learn here is the
reward starting from the state I am not trying
to predict the next state it is entirely possible
for you to write the expression for st + 1
in terms of st but not V hat st + 1 in terms
of Vhat st does that make sense no we talk
we can talk off line right yeah they stopped
I actually had some other public and talk
about it later anyway so that is TD(0) right
so any other questions on TD(0) okay good.
So I am going to talk a little bit about some
time to make it give you a clearer as to what
the difference between Monte Carlo and TD
methods would give you right so we start off
with a very simple data set right.
.
So I am going to give you as a terminal state
after that right
so is the sequence of states and rewards that
you have observed let us assume the policy
is very dumb policy okay because I am doing
evaluation right the policy is fixed I do
not have to worry about the actions so whatever
is the policy right I just observe the sequence
of states and rewards words right so what
is the value of A what is the value of B if
I use Monte Carlo where if you say let us
say I use first to set Monte Carlo let us
keep things simple I use first visit Monte
Carlo so what is the value of A what is the
value of B or let me make things even simpler.
Let us have no first visit every visit business
so what is the value of A the last one is
not critical for our example so well let us
keep calm acquire 4/3 right what about B
so here okay I will make your phases let us
not have 7 case okay so this is essentially
a Monte Carlo estimate
they make a mistake here.
.
Hey sorry guys I made a mistake in the number
I just cooked up some numbers suggest you
realize now both Monte Carlo and TD will give
you the same answers so I need to give you
a set of numbers where Monte Carlo entity
will give you different answers okay it is
Monte Carlo kicked we have A is 1 + 2 / 3
so 1, B is 3/ 6 this 1/2 okay so what will
be the value is estimated by TD so essentially
what you have to do is you have to keep updating
this rule repeatedly till you converge I am
not that cruel okay what you can show which
we lock through or what we can show is that
TD has this amazing property that you are
applying that rule incrementally but it computes
the value function by implicitly constructing
an a Monte Carlo process right.
So if you think about it every time I will
go from A to B right so whenever I update
the value of A I will use the value of B so
in some sense of implicitly encoding that
transition into my updation so it essentially
it looked like something like this so A go
To B and B will go to a terminal series we
can see the right this is with probability
1 all of these transitions will happen right
what is the reward forgoing from A to B okay
the reward is 2/3 the probability is 1 right
like what is expected of all right I am just
removing so what is the work from going from
B to the terminal state right.
So now the value function that the TD update
will converge to is the value function of
a and B in this MDP or in this Monte Carlo
right so what is the value of B in this Monte
Carlo shape that would not change okay here
is the important interesting what is the value
of a in this Markov shape it is the immediate
reward + ? times value of B at ? is 1 7/ 6when
people accept this right so what is the value
of A is the immediate reward plus the value
of the next state right so that is the bellman
equation so the immediate reward is 2/3 the
value of the next state turns out to be half
in this case which we already computed is
7/6 okay.
So we came to a different answer than what
recovery right Monte Carlo gave me one and
half TD is giving me 7/6 and ½ which is the
right answer so you see why TD tells me it
is 7/6 see whenever A occurred before B right
B is been very unrewarding right only one
out of the three tens be gave me 1 but other
times B occurred it has been very rewarding
twice it gave me a 1 and once it gave me 0
okay so what TD methods assume implicitly
is that the whole system is mark of so regardless
of how I came to B when I go out from B I
am going to get that expected reward of half
right but it so happened.
That the few samples I drew from A turned
out to be a bad sample for B right when I
do the Monte Carlo estimates I am getting
a lower value for A because of that I do not
take into account the structure right the
structure is from A I go to B and then I go
to the terminal state and what TD methods
assume is okay from be if you go to the terminal
state this is the reward you are going to
get and therefore from A if you go to B then
you will get whatever reward will get from
going from B to the terminal say it makes
that very strong Markov an assumption right
because it solves for this Markov chain okay.
So now let me go back and ask you which is
the right answer thank you here finally somebody
said it depends on the depends on the problem
and it turns out that what Monte Carlo methods
are doing is essentially trying to minimize
the prediction error right between this particular
set of samples that you have drawn the returns
computer according to these samples alone
right going back to the definition of written
okay it is actually minimizing the squared
error between the value function you get and
the return that you get from this right is
just trying to minimize the squared error
from this fixed set of samples that you get
right.
So what do TD methods do on the other hand
is they form what are called a certainty equivalent
model okay so people in control theory probably
understand this better so there is something
called the certainty equivalent model which
essentially is the model best explains the
data that you have seen so far under certain
assumptions okay so under certain assumptions
you can assume that this model is equivalent
to the system that generated the data that
you have seen so far and in this case we are
making a very strong Markova an assumption.
Then what TD methods try to do is try to make
the prediction according to the certainty
equivalent model I trying to minimize the
error between the value function in the certainty
equivalent model and the predictions you are
making here right so they are optimizing very
different objective functions given an infinite
amount of data drawn from a truly Markova
an system it both will converge to the same
answer but given a finite amount of data right
this will converge to the minimize of the
squared error this will converge to whatever
is the Markov model you can form with that
limited data okay.
This need not be the right model this need
not be the model that gave rise to the data
right given the limited data this is the best
you can do that is all you can see we are
saying here given this data what is the model
you can form it will converge to that right
whether this is the right answer or that is
the right answer given a limited amount of
data depends on what kind of application you
are looking at all the other hand since the
Monte Carlo methods make a less of an assumption
about Markov witness if you suspect that your
system is not very markup okay then do not
use theory methods you are better off probably
better of you see Monte Carlo kind of methods
okay.
But remember I told you that if you use the
notion of a value function already or making
an assumption about Mark of Venus right as
you should be using values of history's right
you should not be using values of states if
you are already using values of states you
have making a Markova assumption but that
is okay right in some sense provided the is
not estimates you are making since then right
you take care of the Markova awareness non-
Markova I think still it is not correct but
at least we will be more robust to violations
of the mark of assumptions and as you can
see very clear from here right just going
by the evidence of the trajectories I have
given you should not think this is a marker
system right so whenever A happens B seems
to have a depressed outcome right display
the evidence of the data here you should not
think it is a Markova system but TD will just
assume it is a Markova system and go ahead
and do the updates okay so you see the difference
between what TD does and Monte Carlo does
okay we will stop here we will worry about
TD control the next class I am still converts
to the thus the least square estimate of the
returns predicted by the data.